<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short and easie introduction to Christian faith conteining the summe of the principles of religion, necessary to be knowne of all before they presume to receiue the sacrament of the Lords Supper: set downe in questions and answers, and distinguished into chapters. By H. Graie.</title>
            <author>Graie, H.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847731</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847731</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12790</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02023)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12790)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 462:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short and easie introduction to Christian faith conteining the summe of the principles of religion, necessary to be knowne of all before they presume to receiue the sacrament of the Lords Supper: set downe in questions and answers, and distinguished into chapters. By H. Graie.</title>
                  <author>Graie, H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegraue, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Churchyard at the signe of the Crane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A catechism.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An introduction to the Christian faith.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12790:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12790:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT AND eaſie introduction to Chriſtian faith: Conteining the ſumme of the principles of Religion, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be knowne of all before they preſume to receiue the Sacrament of the Lords Supper: SET DOWNE IN queſtions and anſwers, and diſtinguiſhed into Chapters.</p>
            <p>By H. GRAIE.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Robert Walde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules Churchyard at the ſigne of the Crane.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno.</hi> 1588.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:12790:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROVERBS. 3. 13.</bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man that findeth wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the man that getteth vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> For the merchandize thereof is better than the merchandize of ſiluer, and the gaine thereof is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the gaine of gold.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Length of daies is in hir right hand, and in hir left hand are ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> She is a tree of life to them which laie hold of hir, and bleſſed is hee which reteineth hir.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12790:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE</hi> Margaret counteſſe of Cumberland, my very good lady, <hi>H. G.</hi> vvisheth comfort and ioy in the Holie ghoſt, vvith continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and increaſe of all ſpirituall graces and bleſſings for the ſuſteining of faith in this preſent vvorld, and in the vvorld to come eternall felicitie in the kingdome of heauen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wiſe man in a moſt heauenly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouerb, as moſt wiſely by his extra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ordinary wiſedome, ſo moſt truly by the inſtinct of the ſpirit, wherwith he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, in writing that booke, hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended it to all poſteritie that the feare<note place="margin">Prou. 3. 7. Pſa. 111. 10</note> of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge, the meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof, and of ſuch like places of holy ſcripture no doubt (right H. and my very good La.) did firſt worke in your ſelfe, an earneſt deſire to know and fear God: &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that godly &amp; zealous care which your Ho. carieth toward your whole family (whereof I my ſelfe vpon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine experience can giue teſtimony) that they might be inſtructed &amp; taught in the knowledge and feare of God. This zeale &amp; carefulnes though it be commendable in al, yet it is ſo much the more commendable, as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in whom it appeareth, is in hier and greater place, &amp; therfore they alſo vnto whom the Lord hath giuen ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor &amp; hath exalted &amp; ſet them aboue other, are eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in regard of their places &amp; the goodnes of god ſhewed to them, to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der thanks to the Lord, by ſhewing obedience to him, &amp; hauing careful ouerſight of them which are vnder their autority &amp; gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: the which the Lord hauing giuen you to ſee, &amp; in ſome good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to deſire to practiſe, &amp; to make an open profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the zeale of gods glory, ſo that the ſame therof is ſpred in moſt places of this land (I hope to the ſturring vp of many by your good example and to the propagation of the praiſe &amp; honor of God) it ſtandeth more neerly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you to labor, to continue, &amp; to go forward, &amp; increaſe in that zealous &amp; godly profeſſion of the ſinceritie and
<pb facs="tcp:12790:3"/> truth of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that God of his goodnes hath more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully dealt with you, may be more glorified by you tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by others vpon whom he hath not beſtowed like graces &amp; bleſſings, &amp; hereof great numbers which onely haue by conſtant report hard of you, do aſſure themſelues &amp; aſſiſt you with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir faithful praiers. And I for mine own part at this preſent (whom it hath pleaſed the right Ho. my Lord, &amp; your La. by the prouidence of God to place ouer your family) as a teſtimony &amp; witnes of your zeale &amp; care of religion, which is better known to me then to others, haue cauſed this ſhort Catechiſme &amp; ſum of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to be publiſhed, which I offer vnto your honor as the greateſt new yeeres gift which my ſmall power in ſo ſudden and ſhort time could preſent you withall, hoping that it ſhalbe accepted in good part, not for the woorthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, but in conſideration of the occaſion, the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and the end your La. had in moouing me to write it. In the handling thereof, as your deſire was, I haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored for breuitie, and by queſtions &amp; anſwers haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued that method which is moſt eaſie &amp; plaine. If by the mercifull goodnes of God (as my deſire &amp; praier is) this ſhort and little treatiſe may redound to the benefit of your familie in regard of that end wherevnto it eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie aimeth; and if your Ho. vnto other your diuers &amp; manifold tokens of your good acceptation of me conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſince my firſt comming into your houſe ſhal adde this, to accept in good part my indeuors and purpoſe, I ſhall thinke my ſelfe abundantly &amp; fullie rewarded, and haue iuſt occaſion offered to aſcend praiſe &amp; glory vnto the Lord, whoſe deuine maieſty from the bottome of my heart I moſt humbly beſeech to grant vnto your honor continuance of health &amp; welfare, and the vſe of all thoſe his gifts and benefits, which both concerne the goods of this life, and eſpeciallie the atteining of life euerlaſting.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ladiships humble bounden in the Lord Ieſus, H. Graye.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:12790:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the Creation of al things,</hi> and fall of man. CHAP. 1.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Queſtion.</speaker>
               <p>WHat thinke you of the frame of this world, and of all things ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, haue they not beene for euer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſwere.</speaker>
               <p>No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p> How were they then firſt made?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>God who is without beginning, &amp; only<note place="margin">Gene. 1.</note> euerlaſting, in the beginning made all theſe things which you ſee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>God is a ſpirit, infinit, eternall, vncrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4. Iere. 23. 24 Apoc. 1. Gene. 1. Iere. 10. 23 Prou. 2. 30 31 Iam. 1. 17.</note> creator and gouernor of all things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out qualitie or quantitie, without ſhadow or change: who is in his eſſence or being infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitlie mightie, iuſt, mercifull and good, and therefore made all things good, and ruleth all things well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Is there but one infinit &amp; one God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>No: but there be three perſons in the<note place="margin">Mat. 28. 19 Iohn. 1. 17. 14 24. Pro. 8. 2 Matt. 3. 17. Ioh. 15. 26.</note> ſame Godhead, the father of himſelfe alone, the ſonne begotten of the father before all beginning, the holie ghoſt proceeding from the father and the ſonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVherfore did God make the world and all creatures therein?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:4"/>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>To ſet foorth his glorie.<note place="margin">Prou. 16.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Seeing God, who is onelie God and without corruption, made all things, how commeth it to paſſe, that euil is come, and the world &amp; all creatures in it are ſubiect to corruption?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Man for whom all things were eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> made, by the ſuggeſtion of ſatan tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the commandement of god brought<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> ſinne into the world, &amp; by ſinne death entred vpon all his poſterity, who had ſinned in him, and moreouer by him the creatures were<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> made ſubiect to vanitie and corruption.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVherefore is the cauſe of ſinne and corruption imputed vnto man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe God hauing made man after<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> his owne image, and giuing him free will and power to continue in that perfect eſtate wherin he was created, he notwithſtanding, abuſing his free will &amp; power which he had to the committing of ſin, is moſt iuſtly to be accounted the cauſe of all ſin, &amp; the excluſion of himſelfe &amp; al his poſterity out of paradiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat call you the image of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Perfect vprightneſſe and integritie in<note place="margin">Eph. 4. Gal. 2.</note> bodie and ſoule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>In what caſe dooth man ſtand now by meanes of Adam his fall?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>We are by nature bondſlaues of ſin &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,<note place="margin">Rom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. Eph. 2.</note> &amp; the children of wrath &amp; condemnation.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:12790:4"/>
            <head>Of the reſtoring of man. CHAP. 2.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p> DOoth man remaine ſtill in that damnable eſtate wherevnto A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam by his fall brought him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>God forbid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the caſe altred with man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>God by his infinit wiſdome, of his only free mercie &amp; goodnes hath ſo diſpoſed, orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red &amp; turned the fall of Adam to the good of his elect children, that their eſtate after this<note place="margin">Roman. 4.</note> life in the kingdome of heuen ſhalbe a great deale more happie &amp; bleſſed than if they had liued in paradiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>By what meanes dooth the Lord worke this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>By fulfilling his promiſe in ſending the<note place="margin">Geneſis. 3. Cor. 1. 15.</note> ſeed of the woman to conquer ſatan, ſin and death, &amp; to ſet vs free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, &amp; to purchaſe for vs euerlaſting life in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kindom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVho is the ſeede of the woman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt Ieſus perfect God &amp; perfect ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, God in that he is of like ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, equall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,<note place="margin">Philipp. 2.</note> eternity &amp; power with his father. Man in that he is the ſeed of the woman, &amp; tooke the whole nature of man vpon him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVas it neceſſarie that our ſauior and redeemer ſhould be both God and man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yea.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q.</speaker>
               <p>VVhy ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:5"/>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>If he had bin man alone, he could not haue paid the ranſome for ſin, &amp; ſatiſfied the infinit wrath of God, but ſhould haue beene ſwalowed vp of death, bicauſe man was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to death. And againe, if he had bin God<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> alone, he could not haue ſuffered death, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was requiſite, that hee ſhould be both God and man, man, that he might die, God, that he might ſuſtaine and vpholde the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> to ouercome and vanquiſh death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>But is it now true, that curſed is hee that dooth not all things which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the booke of the law?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yes verily.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we be freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this curſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>By the death and obedience of Ieſus<note place="margin">Galat. 3.</note> Chriſt: he hath by his death ſuffered the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell for our ſin, &amp; by his obedience performed the whole law for vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>But how dooth that profit vs which Chriſt did in his owne perſon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt is ours by the gift of God, and<note place="margin">Roman. 8.</note> whatſoeuer Chriſt did, hee did not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but he that knewe no ſinne was made ſin for vs, that wee might be the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> of God by him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>By what meanes are we made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſt and his benefits?<note place="margin">Gala. 3. 26. Epheſ. 1.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Onelie by a true faith, whereby wee
<pb facs="tcp:12790:5"/> receiue Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What is faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>It is an vndoubted and certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion of the loue of GOD towardes vs in<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 38 39. &amp; 26, 11</note> Chriſt Ieſus grounded vppon the promiſes of God, made vnto vs in the goſpell, wherby<note place="margin">Roman. 8.</note> wee are aſſured, that our ſins are remitted, &amp; we by the ſpirit of god working in our harts are made the adopted children of God.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>Of the triall of our ſelues whether we <hi>be the children of God, or no.</hi> CHAP. 3.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p> HOw ſhal we know that we haue faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>By proouing our ſelues whether wee<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13. 5</note> be in the faith, or whether Chriſt Ieſus be in vs or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How ſhall wee prooue our ſelues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>By the working of the ſpirit in vs, for<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> thoſe which are the children of God, are led and gouerned by the ſpirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How ſhall we know that the ſpirite dwelleth in vs, and that we haue faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>By the effects and fruits of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Gala. 5. 21.</note> which are loue, peace, long ſuffering, &amp;c. and according to the rule of ſaint Iames: ſhewe<note place="margin">Iames 2.</note> me thy faith by thy works, and I will ſhewe hee my faith by my works.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:6"/>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Are works then neceſſarie to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yea but not as cauſes of our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but as effects and teſtimonies of our faith, and the way which the Lord hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> wherein we ſhould walke and glorifie him, til he bring vs to his kingdom of glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How is this faith begotten in vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The ordinarie meanes is the woorde<note place="margin">Roma. 10. Rom. 1. 18. 1. Pet. 1. 23</note> preached.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Can not they then be ſaued which either haue not the vſe of the word, or els refuſe it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>God forbid that wee ſhoulde iudge or condemne any, for the Lorde can ſaue extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily without meanes, and hee dooth not call all at all times.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Is it no ſinne therfore to refuſe the worde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yes it is a fearefull and dangerous ſin, refuſing the word, and as much as in vs lieth we debarre our ſelues of our ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What cal you the word, the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wherof you make the inſtrument and meanes to beget faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Generally the whole ſcripture which is conteined in that booke commonly called the Bible, but eſpecially the goſpel, wherin theſe cauſes are comprehended wherevpon our faith is grounded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:6"/>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What is the ſpeciall vſe of the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the law?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>It is a forcible meanes to humble vs by the threatnings of the ſame, and it is a<note place="margin">Galat. 3.</note> ſchoolemaiſter to prepare vs, and make vs fit to receiue the goſpell, and Chriſt Ieſus which is offered vnto vs by it.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>Of the law. CHAP. 4.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p> HOw manie things dooth this worde of God generallie taken teach vs principallie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Theſe foure: firſt, obedience to the law of God: ſecondly, praier, which is a part of the worſhip and ſeruice of god: thirdly, faith in Chriſt: fourthlie, the Sacraments which are ſeales &amp; pledges of the doctrine of faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How do you diſtinguiſh theſe foure things according to the vſuall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diuiſion of the woorde into the law and the goſpell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The firſt two inferre vnto the law, and the laſt two vnto the goſpell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How is the law diuided?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Into two tables: Exod. 31. 18. 34. 7.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is conteined in the firſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Our duetie which we owe vnto God, and what ſeruice and worſhip we are to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:7"/>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is conteined in the ſecond?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Our dutie toward our neighbor, and how we ought to behaue our ſelues towards him ſo long as we liue in this world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements be there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Ten.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How many perteine to the firſt table?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The firſt foure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How many to the ſecond?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The laſt ſix.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Rehearſe the commandements.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>God spake theſe words, and ſaid: Thou ſhalt haue no other gods before me, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What is the end and fulfilling of all theſe commandements.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Loue: 1. Tim. 1. Gal. 5. Matth. 22. Nom. 13. Mar. 12.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Is it poſsible for vs to fulfill all theſe without breaking anie one of them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>No, though we do what we can, yet we<note place="margin">Mat. 15. 19 Rom. 17. 18. 19.</note> breake them dailie and hourelie in thought word and deed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What puniſhment then is appointed for the breakers of theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The curſſe of God which is eternall<note place="margin">Deu. 17. 26 Mat. 25. 41</note> deſtruction both of bodie and ſoule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How ſhall we then eſcape this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt became accurſſed for vs to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<note place="margin">Gala. 3.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12790:7"/> vs from the curſſe, and hath nailed that hand-writing which the Lorde had againſt vs vpon the croſſe, and hath made a ſhewe and triumphed openly ouer death, and ouer<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.</note> the curſſe where vnto we were ſubiect.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>Of praier. CHAP. 5.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p> WHat doe wee owe vnto the Lord for this worke of our redemption and our deliuerance from the curſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Al honor, al praiſe, al glorie, al thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How ſhal we giue theſe to the Lord?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>By praier which is vnfained, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from a true and liuelie faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What thing is praier?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>It is an humble lifting vp of our harts and ſoules vnto the Lorde, whereby wee ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make requeſt for things neceſſarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this life and the life to come, or elſe giue thanks vnto God, for benefits and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces receiued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How manie things doe you gather out of this deſcription of praier?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>I obſerue theſe three things: firſt, to whom we muſt pray: ſecondly, for what wee muſt pray: thirdly, the diſtinction or diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:12790:8"/> of praier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>To whom muſt we make our praiers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>To God alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Maye wee not praie to Angels or ſaincts?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>No: for that is flat idolatrie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What reaſon haue you to proue this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>To giue that to the creature which is proper and peculiar to God, is manifeſt ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,<note place="margin">Reue. 9.</note> but praier is a part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice which<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.</note> is dew only to the Lord, therefore to giue it to the creature, it is idolatry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Are not the angels miniſtring ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites for the vſe of man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yes: but we haue no commandement or warant to pray vnto them, for wee muſt<note place="margin">Pſal. 61. Rom. 10.</note> cal vpon him in whom we muſt beleeue, but we muſt beleue in God only &amp; therfore pray vnto him alone and not to angels or ſaincts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>For what cauſe we pray?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>For all things neceſſarie both for this life and the life to come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Muſt we pray for earthly and for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things after the ſame maner?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>No: we muſt pray for earthly things with exception and condicion, ſo far forth as they ſhall ſtand with gods glory &amp; our good, &amp; ſaluation, &amp; thus wee muſt pray for riches, for helth, for proſperity, &amp;c. but we may pray
<pb facs="tcp:12790:8"/> for ſpiritual &amp; heauenly things abſolutely &amp; without condicion, as for faith, ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wiſedome, and ſaluation, for theſe things are alwaies ioyned with the glorie of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How is praier diſtinguiſhed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Into a petition and thankeſgiuing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What is a petition?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>It is a ſute &amp; requeſt which we make vnto the Lord for ſuch things as we ſtand in need of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is thankſgiuing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>It is to acknowledge the Lord to bee<note place="margin">Iames. 1. 1. Cor. 4. 7.</note> the author and fountaine of all goodnes and that we receiue al good things from him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>For what muſt you giue thanks?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>For all benefits both corporal and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. Ierre. 2.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat call you corporall benefits?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>All thoſe which concerne our bodies &amp; the vſe of this life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhich call you ſpirituall?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Al thoſe which concern the welfare of the ſoule and our eternal ſaluation, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, our redemption &amp; deliuerance from death which we mentioned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of this ſection, and all other good graces &amp; benefits which concerne life euerlaſting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How muſt wee pray vnto God, or giue thanks vnto him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:9"/>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>With the ſpirit of our minds, for god<note place="margin">Iohn 4.</note> is a ſpirite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What maner of mind, or with what affection muſt we pray?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>In the affection well diſpoſed vnto praier, theſe foure things are required firſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 18. 13</note> that we renounce our ſelues, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is in vs, and throwe downe our ſelues before the throne of the maieſtie of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging and confeſſing our owne ſins and vnworthineſſe: ſecondly, that wee pray<note place="margin">Iame. 1.</note> in faith: thirdly, that wee haue a feeling of<note place="margin">ve. 6</note> our miſeries, and of the wants and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the which we pray, and that we haue an earneſt deſire to obtaine them: fourthlie, that we come vnto the Lorde with vnfained<note place="margin">Mar. 9. 24.</note> repentance and purpoſe of amendement of life, for the Lord promiſeth no bleſſing to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but to ſuch as are his children, and haue<note place="margin">Roman. 8.</note> a care to walke in his feare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What forme of praier muſt wee vſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>That eſpeciallie which our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe hath preſented vnto vs in the ſixt of Matthew, and ſecond of Luke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>May wee not vſe an other forme of praier beſides this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>We may vſe an other forme of words, but the matter of all our praier muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and limited according to this forme,
<pb facs="tcp:12790:9"/> wherein in generall terms is ſet downe by the wiſeſt that euer was, nay wiſedome it ſelfe, what things we muſt pray for, both concerning this life and the life to come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Repeat this forme of praier which we cal the Lords praier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Our father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Shew me briefly the ſumme and the meaning of this praier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>This praier conſiſteth on thoſe two parts, firſt, a preface in theſe words, <hi>Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which art in heauen,</hi> then the praier it ſelfe in the words following: the preface tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs two things, firſt, what GOD is in reſpect of vs, to wit, a louing father, who as a father tendreth his children, and will not denie him any thing which he hath neede of: ſo the Lord is moſt readie and willing to giue vnto vs ſuch things as are neceſſarie for vs if we aſke them by faith: ſecondly, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt words of this preface, to wit, <hi>which art in heauen,</hi> we are taught what God is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of himſelfe. The examination of the place where the Lord is ſaid to be (not that<note place="margin">1. King. 8. Acts 1. Eſa. 16.</note> he is indeede contained in any place, or can be, bicauſe he is infinit) doth argue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power, the maieſtie, the might of God whereby we are ſure that the Lord is able to grant vs al our requeſts. This preface then doth make
<pb facs="tcp:12790:10"/> much for the ſtrengthning of our faith, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we conſider, that God is a father, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore willing, and he dwelleth in heauen, and therfore is able to giue vs euery thing wee aſke. The praier it conſiſteth vpon certaine petitions, and a concluſion annexed to them: the petitions which are ſixe in number be of two ſorts, the firſt three concerne the glorie of God, the laſt three our owne wants and neceſſities, the order of the firſt three lieth thus: firſt we pray for the glorie of GOD which is the end of all things, that we may celebrate and ſanctifie the name of God: in the ſecond we pray for the meanes that wee may do this, that Chriſt woulde rule by his kingdome in our hearts, and by the working of his ſpirite, thorough the miniſterie of the word, wold be at downe in vs al ſin &amp; wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; raiſe vs vp to ſanctification &amp; holines of life: in the third, that wee may haue aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that we performe both the former, we pray that the wil of god may willingly and readily be done of vs, as the angels doe it in heauen. The order of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> three laſt lieth thus, in the firſt wee pray for al things requiſite &amp; neceſſarie for the maintainance &amp; ſuſtenance of this life: in the two laſt we pray for ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things, &amp; ſuch as concerne life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: in the fift petition we pray for remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:12790:10"/> and pardon of our ſins through Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,<note place="margin">Apo. 20. 27 21. 17</note> without the which we cannot enter into the kingdome of heauen: in the laſt, that the Lord woulde not giue vs ouer vnto ſatan, or ſuffer vs to be ouercommed of temptations, but would deliuer vs from the diuell, and all euil which might hurt &amp; indanger our faith, if the Lord ſhold leaue vs and ſuffer them to rule and tyrannize in vs. The concluſion is <hi>For thine is the kingdome, &amp;c.</hi> which is added for the confirmation and ſtrengthning of our faith, &amp; containeth three arguments: the firſt the Lord is our king, for he wil be mindfull of vs and prouide for his poore ſubiects: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he hath al power, and therfore he wil ſhew it in helping and defending his church &amp; granting his children their requeſts: third<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, to him apertaineth &amp; belongeth al glory, &amp; therfore that his children may glorify him he will giue them ſuch things as they ſhall ſtand in need of, Amen, which is as much as ſo be it, is added for two cauſes: the firſt is to ſhew w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what deuotion or affection we muſt pray, that is, with an ardent &amp; earneſt deſire: ſecondly, with what aſſurance &amp; confidence, to wit, with full perſuaſion that the lord wil grant our deſires.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Do you ſay in this your explication of the lords praier, that the three firſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions
<pb facs="tcp:12790:11"/> concerne Gods glorie, and the three laſt our owne neceſsities?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yea.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>But doe not all concerne the glorie of God which you haue ſaid to be the end of al things?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The firſt three concerne only the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, the laſt 3 do concerne alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of God, but ſo that we alſo pray moreouer, for thoſe things which are needefull for vs both for our ſoules and bodies, that wee by them, and in them we may glorifie God.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>Of faith. CHAP. 6.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p> WHat is the third principal thing which the word teacheth vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The doctrine of faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Vnto what part of the word do you referre this? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Vnto the goſpell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is the goſpell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>It is the glad tidings of ſaluation, &amp; that heauenlie doctrine which teacheth vs how to beleeue to obtaine eternall life tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Ieſus Chriſt onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Is there not a ſumme of the cheefe points of the Goſpell collected and ſet downe ſhortly and briefly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat call you it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The apoſtles creed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhy is it ſo called?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:11"/>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe as ſome thinke it was made by the apoſtles, but rather becauſe it agreeth with their doctrine and that beleefe which they preached in their time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Rehearſe the articles of the creed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>I beleeue in God the father almightie, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How is this creed diuided?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Into twelue articles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How many things doo theſe articles teach vs principally?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Foure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Which be they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Firſt we are taught what to beleue of God the father in the firſt article. 2. What to beleeue of God the ſonne in the ſix next. 3 What to beleeue of God the holy ghoſt in the eight article. 4. What to beleeue concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the church in the foure laſt articles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What doo you beleeue of God the father?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Firſt I beleeue that he is my father in<note place="margin">Eſay. 69. 6. Rom. 58.</note> his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. 2. That he is the founteine of all things, and the maker &amp; cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of them. Laſtlie, that he is almightie,<note place="margin">Iob. 31. 2.</note> and hath power to doo all things, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his prouidence nothing can be doone by men, by angels, or by the diuels in earth, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, or in hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What doo you beleeue concerning
<pb facs="tcp:12790:12"/> the ſecond perſon in trinitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>I beleeue that he is Ieſus, that is my ſauior and redeemer. 2. That he is Chriſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 1. 1.</note> that is the annointed king, preeſt &amp; prophet. 3. That he ſuffered the torments of hell for<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> me vpon the croſſe, and truly, and not feined<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, died for my ſins, &amp; roſe again from death for my iuſtification. 4. That he is aſcended<note place="margin">Rom. 25. Acts. 1.</note> vp into heauen, &amp; there ſhall remaine till the latter day, and then he ſhall come accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the holy angels to iudge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world.<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 32</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What doo you beleeue of the holie ghoſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Firſt that he is God. <hi>1. Pet. 1. 2. Eph. 4.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts. 5. 3. 4 Luke. 1. 15 Iohn. 3. 5. 1. Cor. 5. 5. 28.</note> Secondlie that he doth ſanctifie me, &amp; make me a new creature, and aſſure me of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What doo you beleeue concerning the church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>I beleue that Chriſt hath, and hath had, and ſhall haue till the end of the world in all places, and amongſt all ſorts of men, his<note place="margin">Act. 10. 34. Eph. 5. 34. 1. Cor. 12. 12. 13. 14. 1. Cor. 10. 2. Cor. 11. 28. Galat. 1. 2. Eſa. 53. 4. 5</note> church, that is a company of elect &amp; faithfull people, which haue a ſocietie &amp; fellowſhip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelues, as members of one head whereby they communicat all benefits both ſpirituall &amp; temporall, to whom the Lord gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth remiſſion &amp; pardon of ſins in this life, and in the world to come life euerlaſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:12790:12"/> that he hath raiſed them vp from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 8. 1. Cor. 15. 53. 54. 1. Theſ. 4. 14 1. Cor. 15.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>By what meanes doo we apprehend and atteine to this which you haue now confeſſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The ordinarie way is the hearing and preaching of the word of God, whereby the holie ghoſt dooth worke faith in our hearts<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 2. 3.</note> to apprehend &amp; vnderſtand effectually theſe articles of ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>Of the ſacraments. CHAP. 7.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p> HAth the Lord appointed vnto his church no other means to helpe and ſtrengthen faith by but his word?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yea, our ſauior Chriſt prouiding for our weakenes &amp; infirmities, hath giuen vnto vs outward and viſible ſignes, which do repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and as it were, ſet before our eies &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confirmation of our faith, the truth, and if I may ſo ſpeak for more plainnes, the eſpeciall matter of this whereof you haue now made confeſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What call you theſe ſignes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Sacraments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is a ſacrament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>It is an outward and viſible ſigne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and ordained of the Lord to confirm the promiſes and couenants of God made to vs in the goſpel in the hearts of the faithful.<note place="margin">Gen. 17. 11</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:13"/>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What doo you learne out of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Theſe three things. Firſt that it is a ſigne of another thing which is ſignified. 2. That euerie ſacrament muſt haue his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Lord. 3. That it is a pledge or ſeale of the promiſe of ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Why doo you ſay this is a ſigne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe it is a thing which the Lord ſetteth before mens eies, to ſignifie a thing which is not ſeene,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>why muſt it be inſtituted of god only?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>He only muſt appoint the ſeale and the ſigne which giueth the promiſe, but God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie maketh the promiſe of ſaluation, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he onelie hath authoritie to ordeine the ſacrament or ſigne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Why ſay you that it muſt be a pledge or ſeale of the promiſe of ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe it is giuen vs of the Lord for the confirmation of our faith, which is grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the promiſe of ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Are all theſe things neceſſarilie to bee obſerued in euery ſacrament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yea.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t do you make of thoſe fiue which the papiſts haue added, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the ſacraments of penance, abſolution, confirmation, laieng on of hands, extreme vnction, and matrimonie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:13"/>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>That account which the word of God teacheth me to make of them, that they are no ſacraments, becauſe theſe three things which are neceſſarily required in euerie ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, are not to be found in any of them. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How many ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do you make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Two. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhich be they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lord.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is Baptiſme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>It is a ceremony inſtituted of Chriſt in<note place="margin">Matth. 18.</note> a viſible ſigne of water to ſignifie our remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, and reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we haue with God by the blud of Ieſus Chriſt which is ſhed for vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>what do you conſider in this definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Theſe two things (which are alſo to be conſidered in the Supper of the Lord) I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue for the true vſe of the ſacrament. Firſt what is the ſigne. Secondly what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing ſignified. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>what is the ſigne in baptiſm?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Water.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What is the thing ſignified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Remiſſion and pardon of ſinnes by the<note place="margin">Act. 22. Marke. 14.</note> bloud of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>In euery ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t there muſt be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance &amp; proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwixt the ſigne &amp; thing ſignified, tell vs therfore what it is in this ſacrament of Baptiſme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>As the water dooth waſhe awaie the
<pb facs="tcp:12790:14"/> filthineſſe of the bodie, ſo our ſoules being<note place="margin">Ti. 3. 6. 5. 6. Ephe. 5. 20 1. Pe. 1. 1. 2. 1. Iohn. 7.</note> ſprinckled with the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt waſhed and purged from the filthineſſe and pollution of ſinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Is there any difference betwixt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in baptiſme and other water?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Not as concerning the ſubſtance, but they differ in the vſe: for common water ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to waſh the bodie, but water in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is a Sacrament of the waſhing of the ſoule,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVherefore are we but once bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed ſince we are commanded oftentimes to receiue the ſupper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe, as circumciſion was to the<note place="margin">Gen. 17</note> Iewes, ſo baptiſme is to vs an entrance and admiſſion into the church of god, and it is ſufficient for vs once to be admitted into gods familie, and therfore as they were but once circumciſed, ſo wee muſt be but once baptized: yet that we may remaine and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in this familie and church of god, it is neceſſarie that wee be fedde oftentimes, and therefore we muſt often receiue the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſupper, as the Iewes did alſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery<note place="margin">Exod. 12.</note> yere celebrate the paſſeouer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What is this ſupper of the Lorde which is the other ſacrament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>It is a ceremonie inſtituted of our
<pb facs="tcp:12790:14"/> ſauiour Chriſt a little before his death in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> ſignes of bread and wine, to teſtifie and repreſent vnto vs his paſſion and bloudſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, whereby he ſuffred the torments of hel for our ſinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What bee the ſignes in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Bread and wine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is the thing ſignified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Our redemtion and deliuerance from<note place="margin">Phil. 8.</note> eternall death and hell by the ſuffering and bloudſhedding of Ieſus Chriſt vppon the croſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is the reſembling and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion betwixt the ſigne and the thing ſignified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>That as our bodies by the hand and mouth receiuing theſe outward things of bread and wine are therby nouriſhed indeed, ſo aſſuredly wee apprehending by faith the<note place="margin">Iohn. 6. 35. Mat. 26. 26 Rom. 4. 23. 1. cor. 30. 2. cor. 5. 21</note> paſſion and bloudſhedding of Ieſus Chriſt, our ſoules are thereby nouriſhed and fed to eternall life, hauing our ſins remitted, and Chriſts death &amp; righteouſnes imputed to vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What doeth the bread ſignifie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The body of Chriſt.<note place="margin">1. cor. 11. 24</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What doth the wine ſignifie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>The bloud of Chriſt.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 25</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Why hath the Lord iuſtituted two
<pb facs="tcp:12790:15"/> ſignes in the ſupper, and but one in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>As our bodies are not ſuſtained by meat only, but alſo by drinke, ſo the Lorde would aſſure vs that we are not fed to halfs, as it were, but Chriſt hee is both meat and drinke vnto vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Is the bread and wine in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſame with other commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bread and wine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>They are the ſame in ſubſtance and<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 16. 17. 18. 1. Cor. 11. 26. Mat. 26. 28</note> nature, but the holie vſe wherevnto they are applied, make them differ from common bread and wine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Is not the bread turned into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt, and the wine into the bloud of Chriſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>But doth not our ſauior Chriſt ſay, this is my bodie, when he gaue the bread, and this is my bloud, when hee gaue the wine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yea, but they are figuratiue ſpeeches at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing the name of the thing ſignified, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing ſignifieng, as alſo in the old ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. Circumciſion was called the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant which was but a ſigne of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,<note place="margin">Gene. 17. Exod. 12. 1. Cor. 10.</note> and the paſchall lambe was called the paſſeouer, and the rocke was called Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:15"/>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is the reaſon why the ſigne is called by the name of the thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe we ſhould lift vp our minds from theſe earthly and corporal things vnto the heauenly and ſpiritual things which are ſignified by them.</p>
               <p>To what end doe we receiue this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the ſupper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>For theſe three cauſes principallie.<note place="margin">Mal. 26.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, for the redemtion and ſtrengthning of our faith.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for a teſtification of our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 26. Mat. 26.</note> and thankefulneſſe vnto God for the worke of our redemption.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, for increaſe of loue and amitie,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 17. 1. Cor. 12. 13. 1. Cor. 11. 33. Epheſ. 4. 5.</note> for there is alwayes a communion of ſaints in the church of God, which eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in this, that all the children of God are members of the ſame bodie, and parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the ſame Sauior and Redeemer Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Seeing the bodie of Chriſt is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and we are on earth, how are we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Thorough a true and a liuelie faith<note place="margin">Iohn 3. 17.</note> which diſcendeth and taketh hold of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of GOD in the merites of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12790:16"/>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>That we may be woorthy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants of this ſacrament, how muſt we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelues vnto it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>We firſt muſt try &amp; examine our ſelues concerning the doctrine of a ſacrament whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we do rightly vnderſtand or conceiue of it or no. Secondly alſo concerning our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners &amp; life, whether we be fit to receiue it at the time appointed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How muſt we examine our ſelues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the doctrine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>By entring into conſideration of that which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt hath written &amp; ſet downe of it, whether we do fully vnderſtand &amp; know it, and whether our hearts and conſciences can willingly ſubſcribe and yeeld vnto it which is taught to be the truth of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Is this examination of our ſelues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the doctrine neceſſary?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Yea, otherwiſe how ſhal we know how to behaue our ſelues in this holy action, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we know what it is that we do, and for what end and purpoſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How muſt we examine our ſelues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our maners and life, whether we be fit to receiue this ſacrament or no?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>By prouing our ſelues whether we be<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13. 5. 1. Cor. 11. 28.</note> the members of Chriſt or no.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How ſhall we know this great ſecret
<pb facs="tcp:12790:16"/> and myſterie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>If we haue faith and repentance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How ſhal I decerne that I haue faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>If in my heart I be aſſuredly perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">Ephe. 1. 13 2. Cor. 1. 22. 5. 5. Rom. 8. 15. Ephe. 3. 12 1. Iohn. 2. 1 Eſay. 53. 6. Epheſ. 17. 18</note> by the working of the ſpirit in me, that the puniſhment of my ſin is fully diſcharged in Chriſt, and that whatſoeuer he hath done perteineth not onely vnto others but euen to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>How ſhall I know that I haue true repentance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>If I be inwardly and heartily ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 75 Iere. 4. 4. Ioel. 2. 12. Rom. 6. 45. 6. 7. Phil. 3. 13. 14</note> for my ſins, and doo moſt willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them vnto God, with full deliberacion and purpoſe of amendment of life, &amp; an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire to mortifie and kill ſin in me, and wholy to conforme my ſelfe to too the will of the Lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>What if I find not theſe things in me, what counſell giue you me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>Not to preſume to come to this table of the Lord, for he that eateth and drinketh<note place="margin">1. cor. 11.</note> vnwoorthilie (that is, without faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, whileſt he is a wicked liuer, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane perſon, a blaſphemer, &amp;c. and hath not repented him of his ſins, with full purpoſe to renounce them, and liue alwaies after in the feare of God) he eateth and drinketh his owne condemnation, not decerning the body
<pb facs="tcp:12790:17"/> of Chriſt aright.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <p>Is it a thing left to our choiſe and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie whether we will come to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>No, the holie ghoſt in forbidding men to come thither vnworthily commaundeth al them which haue diſcretion and iudgement, to examine diligentlye, and prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that they may come worthily vnto it: ſo that if wee do abſent our ſelues, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this preparation &amp; making of our ſelues readie to come vnto it, let vs feare leaſt we become contemners of it, and ſo depriue our ſelues of that great benefite which is offered vnto vs by it.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:12790:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
